Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ס"ו, Samech Vav,
66, and we pick up at the very top, and the גמרא
Gemara is having an interesting question, discussion, which is we've been talking
about what happens if you need—the blood spills or one of the
goats die and you have to bring another one or one of
them gets lost, the goat or the cow. What do you do
with the one that's left over? So there's a debate between רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים. Chachamim. The חכמים Chachamim say you
let it graze,
חטאת הציבור, Chatas HaTzibur, a communal חטאת Chatas you let graze even
if you wound up using a different one, and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says you let it die. And the גמרא’s Gemara question is
based on a position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says if
you gave money for the שקל Shekel and it wound up that
you found the old money that was given that you can advance
that money towards next year, why not, even though you've sanctified this
animal for this year, this cow or this goat, why don't you
just leave it for next year? So you can't use it this
year, leave it for next year.
So the גמרא Gemara has been going back and forth with different
answers, some work for the cow, some work for the goat, it
has to be a גזירה. Gezira. The most recent answer seems to
be the most obvious, that at least for the goat,
if by next year it'll be more than a year old and
the goat has to be within a year, such an obvious answer
you wonder why the גמרא Gemara didn't give it up front. And
then the גמרא Gemara even says even a stranger thing, which is
that oh, it's a גזירה Gezira it won't be a year old.
So the גמרא Gemara says who needs a גזירה? Gezira? It won't
be a year old, it won't be a year old! So it
says well, רבי, Rebbi, who says that when you sell a house
in a walled city, because the תורה Torah says שנה תמימה, Shana
temima, a full year, you go by a solar year, theoretically it's
possible sometimes that the goat itself will be within its first solar
year, so you have to say גזירה, Gezira, which is strange. Number
one, why deal with such a far-fetched case? And number two, since
when does רבי Rebbi say that that applies to the age of
animals? He says it's specifically about a walled city. And you wouldn't
take גזירה, Gezira, you'd fundamentally say it won't be a year old.
So there's one case in a million that it will be a
year old, so okay, that's לא פלוג. Lo pelug. Anyway, that's the
base, so it's not exactly clear why the גמרא Gemara focuses on
that. But the basic answer is the reason you can't use the
goat for next year is because it won't be a year old.
But the גמרא Gemara is not done, so we pick up on
the top of ס"ו עמוד א'. Samech Vav Amud Aleph. Let's take
a look.
Top of the first line. התינח שעיר, Hateinach Se'ir, that explains why
you can't use the goat for next year. פר מאי איכא למימר,
Par mai ika lemeimar, what about not using the ox for the
next year? Although the גמרא Gemara before said maybe the reason not
to use the פר, Par, ox, was really a גזירה, Gezira, because
maybe the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would die and then it would
be an ox that the owners had died. So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, גזירה פר אטו שעיר, Gezira Par atu Se'ir, we won't
let you use the ox for next year because you might come
to use the goat, and the goat has the problem that it'll
be more than a year old. But the ox is good as
long as it's three years—within three years. Now there's even a question
about that as well because the ox also has to be within
a specific age.
It can't be too young because then it's called an עגל, Agel,
then it's called a calf, not an ox. But based on different
versions of a משנה Mishnah in פרה, Parah, there seems to have
been a range, maybe between two to three years or three to
four years, there's a position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that three
years and up, no matter how old it is. So somehow you
have more latitude by an ox how old it is. So why
is that an issue of using it next year? And the גמרא
Gemara now says it's a גזירה. Gezira. But the גמרא Gemara is
still not happy. It says ומשום גזירה ימות, Umishum gezira yamut, just
because of this type of a גזירה? Gezira? תוספות Tosafot has a
long discussion that there might be other גזירות Geziras that are more
reasonable that we'll say let the animal die. But this גזירה, Gezira,
which seems pretty far-fetched, this one you're going to say it has
to die? והא
חטאת שעברה שנתה, Veha chatas she’avrah shnasah, and now let's get back
to the goat. You said the reason not to use the goat
next year and to have it die is because it'll be more
than a year old. But actually once it's more than a year
old, if it's too old, לרעיה אזלא, Lir’iyah azla, it doesn't—it's the
normal הלכה Halacha by that, even by a private חטאת, Chatas, is
not that it dies, but that it's set out to pasture. דאמר
ריש לקיש, De'amar Resh Lakish, because ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, חטאת
שעברה שנתה, Chatas she’avrah shnasah, if you have a חטאת Chatas that
the reason you can't bring it as a קרבן Korban is because
it's more than a year old, so רואין אותה כאילו היא עומדת
בבית הקברות, Ro'in osah ke'ilu hi omedes b'veiss hakvaros, it's not like
there's some intrinsic invalidity in the animal and therefore you have to
be let die like you do by other חטאות Chatasos you can't
bring. It's more like it's inaccessible. This is a sort of a
metaphor for describing it as being inaccessible. You see it as if
it's standing in a cemetery, ורועה, Vero'eh, and you let it graze,
but you don't—you can't use it, but it's not like it's some
פסול, Psul, invalidity. Now it's funny that the גמרא Gemara takes that
for granted because often the list of the five חטאות Chatasos that
die, one that is more than a year old is on that
list. But that is debated. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says that just
because it's more than a year old you don't let it die.
So the גמרא Gemara says right now, again, the question is why
does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say if you didn't use the goat
you let it die? Until now we've been focusing on the fact
that he says a communal חטאת. Chatas. would die and it's not
like the rabbis say you let it graze. But גמרא Gemara say
I still don't get why you let it die. Why not hold
it over and use it to next year? So the first answer
is well, cuz it'll be more than a year old. And even
though that's not a concern by the ox, but we put them
all in the same category. But now the גמרא Gemara says first
of all, I'm still unhappy about the ox, it's just גזירה gezera
you shouldn't let it die. And number two, even if you've explained
to me why you can't use it next year because it'll be
more than a year old, but even by private sacrifices, at least
according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, we don't let them die when
they're too old, we let we just let them graze. So we
still don't guess why just because you didn't use it, you let
it die. Either let use it next year, or even if there's
a concern that it'll be too old by next year, let it
graze, don't let it die. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara
answer is. And now the גמרא Gemara says what Michael was asking
yesterday, אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so here's what רבא Rava
says. Here's the reason you don't wait till next year to use
these animals. גזירה משום תקלה, Gezera mishum takala,
it's a concern of stumbling, meaning it's a concern that you will
come to accidentally misuse it. You have this animal waiting around the
whole year to be used next year that we're afraid that you're
going to come to accidentally derive benefit from it and transgress. דתניא
Detanya we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, אין מקדישין ואין מעריכין ואין
מחרימין בזמן הזה. Ein makdishin ve'ein maarichin ve'ein machrimin bazman hazeh.
You don't sanctify animals for either for בדק הבית Bedek Habayis or
for קרבנות. Korbanot. You don't מעריך maarich is also the way of
of accepting upon yourself to pay the value of something to הקדש,
Hekdesh,
and you don't and you're not מחרימין, machrim, which is also which
is another term to use which also transfers objects sanctifies objects for
the Temple Treasury nowadays. You don't do that. ואם הקדיש והעריך והחרים,
Ve'im hikdish vehe'erich vehecherim, so in the simple sense here we're not
talking about קרבנות. Korbanot. I said מקדישין makdishin is קרבנות, Korbanot, but
actually מקדיש makdish is general הקדש Hekdesh to בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis.
If you sanctify anything nowadays to בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis, what do
you do? So בהמה, Behema, if it's an animal, תעקר, Te'aker, you
let you basically you literally you
like hamstring it. Thank you, that's the word. We'll see what that
means in a minute. The גמרא Gemara will describe that. But basically
you either let it be destroy you let it go to waste
or you actually physically destroy it.
פירות כסות וכלים, Peirot ksut vekeilim, fruit and and clothing, ירקבו, Yirakvu,
you let rot. So you don't actively destroy it, but you let
them rot. מעות וכלי מתכות, Ma'ot uchlei matachot, money and and metal
objects, יוליכם לים המלח, Yolichem leyam hamelach, you throw it into the
Dead Sea. Now it's actually an interesting phrase here because it says
יוליך הנאה. yolich hana'ah. The הנאה hana'ah normally means you transfer the
value to some money and you throw it. Why this do you
transfer the value? The other stuff also why not transfer the value?
And תוספות Tosafot actually asks that question. תוספות Tosafot says why do
you have to let these stuff, you know, rot? Why not just
transfer קדושה? kedusha? If it's not a קרבן korban you can transfer
קדושה, kedusha, transfer קדושה kedusha to some money. There's actually even another
teaching that nowadays since the actual treasury is not going to benefit
from it, there's no treasury to give it to, you can actually
transfer it in a way that's not of equal value. So you
have something of a thousand dollars, you transfer it to one dollar.
So הקדש Hekdesh isn't losing out, it's just the if you would
the metaphysical status of הקדש, Hekdesh, it's not actually the money's going
to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, there is no בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash fund nowadays. And take that one dollar and throw it into
ים המלח. Yam Hamelach. So תוספות Tosafot says there actually are some
cases where we do that, but here we don't. And presumably one
of the reasons we don't is not just we want to make
you avoid in this particular case misusing it, we want to actually
there to be, you know, there to be something punitive. We want
actually it to
be to prevent people from getting in the habit of doing this.
So we don't make it too easy, maybe punitive was too harsh
a word. But anyway, we don't make it too easy to solve
the problem. So you so anyway the phrase here הנאה hana'ah is
a little strange. It could be that in this case it really
just means you throw the whole thing into ים המלח. Yam Hamelach.
So why do you do that? Now, the גמרא Gemara says wait
we're not done, ואיזו היא עיקור, Ve'eizo hi ikur, what does it
mean to hamstring? So it doesn't literally mean to disfigure the animal,
but נועל דלת בפניה ומתה מאליה. No'el delet befaneha umeta me'eleha. You
lock the door in front of it, you lock it in a
pen and you let it die. So you basically don't too much
actively destroy it, you let it go to waste because that would
also be a concern about ביזיון הקדש. bizayon hekdesh. I mean, you
know, you know, disregard of הקדש Hekdesh to actually to take something
that's sanctified and to physically destroy it.
So but you let it go to waste. Exactly what it means
by the meadow case, do you actually throw it in the ים
המלח, Yam Hamelach, not clear. But anyway, the basic point is you
do something to actively make it so that you have no access
to it and it's going to get destroyed and it's going to
go to waste. Why? So it shouldn't be sitting around, thank you
so much, it shouldn't be sitting around and you should come to
misuse it. So you see that that's a concern. So there here
also your question is just wait till next year, at least that's
your concern by your ox, by the goat maybe we get it,
but anyway But the goat, even the goat, the question is just
let it graze. Our answer is, no, we don't want it hanging
around because you're going to get to be misused and therefore we're
going to put it in a situation where it just dies. And
that's why we say מיתה. Misa. So now, I'll take the questions
in a minute, but let's just read. The Gemara might already ask
some of your questions. The Gemara says, one minute. תקלה דמאי, Takala
demai, what how what type of stumbling, misuse are we concerned about?
אי תקלה דהקרבה, I takala de-hakrava, if we're concerned that you might
actually come and offer it as a sacrifice. This animal can't be
a sacrifice. Why? Well, between now and next because it was sanctified
for a different purpose. And between now and next year anyway, so
between now and next year you can't use it. And next year
it'll be too old. So anyway, if the concern is you'll come
to use it, misuse it as a
sacrifice, אפילו כל רעיות נמי, Afillu kol re'uyot nami, so I don't
get it, all sin offerings that you're not allowed to use and
that we say, or all animals that you're not allowed to use
and we say let them graze until they get a blemish and
transfer the value, right that's what we say about a number of
animals that for some reason you couldn't use it, we say let
it graze, it'll get a blemish, you'll transfer the value. Why aren't
we concerned that you'll come to misuse it? Why are we—why do
we let those graze and we don't let this graze? So the
Gemara says,
אי תקלה דהקרבה אפילו כל רעיות נמי. I takala de-hakrava afillu kol
re'uyot nami. אי תקלה דגיזה ועבודה, I takala de-giza va-avoda, so let's
say there's another concern. Not you might actually offer it even though
it can't be used right now in the interim. We're concerned you'll
misuse it like I said, you'll come to shear it or you'll
work it and you'll get benefit from it. Same question. אפילו כל
רעיות נמי. Afillu kol re'uyot nami. So all animals that we say
you let them graze till they get a blemish, let's be concerned
that in the interim you'll come to misuse it. So the Gemara
says,
לעולם תקלה דהקרבה. Le-olam takala de-hakrava. Yeah, the concern is like you
said, you might come to accidentally offer it and it's not fit
to be offered because it's certainly—it's not next Yom Kippur, even if
we bracket the concern of the age. So the Gemara says, הנך
דלאו בר הקרבה נינהו לא טריד בהו. Henakh de-lav bar hakrava ninhu
lo tarid behu. Those that you'll never be able to bring, a
certain type of an animal that you have to let get a
blemish and you'll transfer the value, and this animal itself nobody is
ever suggesting that you could bring this animal itself. The most you
could do is transfer the value. So you like ignore them, you
put them out to pasture, you're not even thinking about them. They're
not even—it's not even possible to bring the animal itself. So you're
not involved in them.
הא דבר הקרבה הוא טריד בה. Ha de-bar hakrava hu tarid bah.
This one that you're saying that by next Yom Kippur you'll be
able to bring, so טריד בה, tarid bah, you're still involved in
it, you're still—your mind is still on it. And therefore you might
accidentally—you're still thinking, 'Ah, next Yom Kippur I'm going to bring it,
next Yom Kippur I'm going to bring it,' you're constantly thinking about
using it. So it might be on your mind so you might
come to accidentally use it even before Yom Kippur for a different
purpose. I know, I know. I don't really get this. Okay. So
the basic answer is the following. Let's just step back and say
what the answer was and then you can ask me all your
questions. So the case of the goat, that won't be usable next
year. That's easy. So that won't be usable next year, so we
understand why you don't hold it over till next year because it
won't be usable.
And there you can't also say תקלה takala because we've just decided
it's not usable next year. So the case of the goat, that's
why you have to let it die. Now, what do you do
about Resh Lakish that says an animal that's more than a year
old you let graze and you don't let die? It's not so
clear how we've answered that with the case of the goat. We'll
get back to that in a minute. The case of the cow,
of the ox, that although in theory you could let wait till—to
hold over and use next year, we're saying we don't want you
to because if we let you wait it till next year, you're
going to accidentally come to bring it sooner. You know you have
it set aside as the animal that you're going to use for
next year, your mind is on it, and therefore we're afraid that
you're going to come to misuse it and you'll use it even
earlier. Whereas animals that are never going to go to the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, you just put them out to pasture and therefore you let
them—and you don't think about them, and therefore we're not concerned about
misuse. That's the Gemara's answer. Now, well, let me take some questions.
Yes, Michael you have a—okay. Rivka? I want to understand why
there's no צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim.
Yeah, yeah. We seem to completely forget about צער בעלי חיים tza'ar
ba'alei chayim issues in this context.
Very shocking
that
they are instituting such extreme cruelty
on
the off chance that somebody might make a mistake. Therefore, they're telling
you to
torture—to torture this animal.
Yeah, I know.
I—whereas some of them get sent out to pasture, in a way
it's like two tiers. Some of them go on to lead a
happy life, not sacrificed, they just are
in pasture until they get a מום. mum. Left to die. Left
to die. Yeah,
I have a real problem with this. Yeah, it's true about all
the
cases about Well,
presumably the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash takes it over once it's been
sanctified and also let die.
Somewhere in the temple, that's totally...
Well, I don't know, in the temple, somewhere on temple grounds, wherever
temple has its pasture grounds, actually. Yeah.
How can you tolerate it in light of holiness?
Yeah, no, you're right, it's very disturbing because you're exactly right, you
know, it's sort of like these ritual concerns of sanctity, whatever, overriding,
you know, sort of basic issues of empathy and, you know, moral
sensibilities. I mean, you're right, you're absolutely right. I don't have an
answer for it.
And the תורה Torah seems to be constantly concerned that if you
see a donkey under its load, help it, and this is the
opposite. Right, right.
Look, I will say that, right, right. Look, you know, some of
the ראשונים Rishonim do bring evidence from this or similar cases, like
this case of תעקר te'aker specifically they make reference to, in terms
of demonstrating that sometimes the הלכה halacha of צער בעלי חיים tzar
ba'alei chayim can be overridden for, for like legitimate purposes, human concerns.
And they talk about like, you know, let's say animal experimentation
in terms of in terms of medical necessity and so on.
But these animals have no use.
Well, the argument is is that the same way
you
could do it for, you know, for the same way you could
do it for testing cosmetics, I'm not sure you agree with that
either, but you know, but you know, if you could use animals
for those types of purposes and allow them to suffer, you know,
you can do it for helping a human being. Well, it's helping
them in the sense of ritual observance. What? How? How?
By preventing them from sinning, by preventing them from transgressing. I understand,
I understand. It's a problem. Yeah, though, I don't really have an
answer though, רבקה. Rivka.
Yeah, so I'm embarrassed I have a very mundane question. What's the
difference between כסות ksud and כלים? keilim?
Oh, כלים keilim
are like just vessels like...
No, כסות ksud is usually clothes? No, no, no, but it could
also be like כלי מתכות, klei matachot, like metal vessels.
It could be... No, they referenced that in the difference. No, they
didn't, where?
They had כלי מתכות, klei matachot, metal ones.
What about my, what about my dishes? Fine, so the כלים keilim
there... Yeah.
And any type of utensils, right.
Okay. But I have to tell you, I don't even fully understand
this answer either. Number one, I don't understand how it solves the
ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, who said that even after a year you
let it graze, so you don't let it die, so then I'm
still trying to figure this out. Let's think, because a goat, it's
not fit for being brought, it can only graze because after a
year from now it will no
longer, it'll be too old... right? So it's like any animal that
won't be fit that you let graze, we don't have this concern
that you're going to bring it and therefore you're more likely to
misuse it, number one. And we still haven't answered why you let
it die, it should be let graze. So I don't understand. It
answers the ox, that according to the ox, if we let it
stay around, it'll be fit for being brought next year because it's
fit for being brought, we're concerned that that'll lead to misuse, although
as was pointed out that's quite ironic. But the goat, you know,
it'll never be fit for use, so why shouldn't that be like
any animal that's not fit for use you let graze, unless we're
rejecting ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, and unless we're saying that even more
than a year old you have to let die. So I still
don't fully get the answer.
There's another issue. Yes. You can't, I don't think a person can
make a pragmatic, well, you can't introduce pragmatics into an ethical argument.
In other words, in this world view, there's something metaphysical at stake,
just like in a biological natural sciences world view, there's something physical
at stake. So if a person claims cruelty should trump everything else,
you can't be cruel, you can't derive benefit on the coattails of
cruelty, so then that's the ethical argument that would, should apply to
experimentation with animals as well as this type of situation. Here we
don't buy into the metaphysics of it, but in this world view,
the metaphysics was as real as the sciences for us today. I
mean, I'm not disagreeing with you, I'm just trying to look at
the structure of the argument.
I know, I just want to point out what we said when
we set a status of an animal instead of an object, like
blood דם, dam, נפש nefesh and all that, and we are, it's
like we're giving ourselves to God, קהלת Kohelet says it's a very
high, you know, on a metaphysical level, that's fine. But this is
to take that, that same animal, instead of sacrificing it, to torture
it. Right, right.
Yeah, it is very difficult. Yeah, it's very difficult, you know, I
think דב Dov is right in terms of the mindset.
Right. Okay,
I see now the problem. Let's go on.
Yeah, and one might have—have any of the archaeologists found coins at
the bottom of the Dead Sea?
Oh, I don't know. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ובתקלה עצמה ובתקלה עצמה תנאי היא. u-v-takala atzma u-v-takala atzma Tannai hi.
The debate of whether we're concerned about תקלה takala by an animal
that you have to let wait over, you know, and that you
might want to hold over for the next year. As we said,
normally when you sanctify things לבדק הבית l'vedek ha-bayit nowadays, destroy them.
When you sanctify it for a קרבן korban when there was a
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you let it graze to get a
blemish, that's fine, let it graze. We've created now a new category
that sanctify something that can be used later and holding it over
till it can be used is different than letting it graze to
get a blemish, and that type of a thing we are concerned
of misuse and that type of an animal we would say let
die. That's the new idea we've just put out there. That's the
issue about the goat and the ox. Don't wait till next year.
If you don't hold it over for use—holding it over for use
is a concern of stumbling and therefore you have to let it
die. So the גמרא Gemara says that itself is a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Baraita. דתניא חדא,
De-tanya chada, פסח שלא קרב בראשון, Pesach she-lo karev be-Rishon, if you
have a קרבן korban you sanctify for a פסח Pesach and you
didn't bring on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, יקרב בשני, yikarev be-Sheni,
give it to somebody who needs a פסח שני Pesach Sheni who's
going to be bringing it in אייר Iyar and give it to
him. בשני, Be-Sheni, if it wasn't brought on פסח שני, Pesach Sheni,
יקרב לשנה הבאה, yikarev l'shana ha-ba'ah, use it for the next year.
Now how do you use it for the next year? How is
it still within a year old? So let's assume that it was—I
don't know—according to רבי, Rebbi, it's not a solar year. Okay. ותניא
אידך, Ve-tanya idach,
we taught in another ברייתא, Baraita, לא יקרב, lo yikarev, don't use
it for the next year. מאי לאו בתקלה פליגי, Mai lav be-takala
pligi, must be they debate this issue of stumbling. Can you hold
it over for a year to use it a year later? So
it's not that it's going to graze to get a blemish where
we allow. It's not בדק הבית bedek ha-bayit which we explicitly say
you do destroy it. It's a קרבן korban that you want to
hold over for a year. And here it's debated. So maybe that's
the issue. Do we let you hold your קרבן korban over for
a year? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, that's not necessarily
the debate. דכולי עלמא לא חיישינן לתקלה, De-kulei alma lo chayshinan l'takala,
everybody says we're not concerned of stumbling. Or you could have said
the opposite גרסא, girsa, everybody says we are concerned. But anyway, my
גרסא girsa says everybody says we're not concerned of stumbling. Normally you
would hold a קרבן korban over for a year. That's not a
concern. The same way you would let a קרבן korban graze and
you're not concerned, you'd hold it over for a year. והכא בפלוגתא
דרבי ורבנן קמיפלגי, Ve-hacha bi-plugta de-Rebbi ve-Rabanan kamiflagi, here it's a different
debate. דלא קשיא הא רבי הא רבנן. De-la kashya ha Rebbi ha
Rabanan. Because as I said, how do you get a פסח Pesach
a year later that's still a year old? So the issue isn't
can you hold it over for a year, are you concerned of
misuse? The question is can you get a פסח Pesach a year
later that's still a year old? So you can only get that
according to רבי Rebbi that says you go by the solar year.
So the one that said you can wait till next year held
like רבי, Rebbi, you go by solar year and it's possible next
year it'll still be a year old. Whereas according to the רבנן,
Rabanan, of course you can't use it next year. It's not going
to be—it's going to be more than a year old. So the
גמרא Gemara says that explains that ברייתא. Baraita. But ותניא, ve-tanya, we
have another ברייתא Baraita that says וכן מעות, ve-chen ma'ot, similarly if
you sanctified money for a פסח, Pesach, there's a debate: do you
hold the money over for next year or do you not? So
if you sanctified money, why shouldn't you hold it over for next
year? אלא לאו שמע מינה דבתקלה פליגי, Ela lav shma mina de-be-takala
pligi, you see the debate is is whether there's a concern of
misuse if you want to hold it over for next year, is
there a concern of misuse? שמע מינה, Shma mina, so that is
a good argument. So what we see is the following: that when
it comes to sanctifying things nowadays where you have to hold it
indefinitely till there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for forever, you sanctify
something for the temple treasury, so an indefinite sanctity it's going to
be sitting around your house and sanctified, there there's a clear concern
of misuse, there you have to destroy it. But what about you
sanctify something not nowadays when there's no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, when
there is a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you sanctify it for
a קרבן korban and you can't use it? So if the idea
is just wait till it gets a blemish and it's something that
you're putting out of your mind, it can't be used anymore, put
it out to pasture, wait till it gets a blemish, you're not
going to use it, that everybody is fine, do it, wait till
it gets a blemish. We're talking about a middle category: that on
the one hand it's not like sanctity nowadays where there's no end
in sight. It's not like the case of being put out to
the pasture where it's out of your mind because it's not fit
for use anymore. It's just an issue of holding it over for
a year. You sanctified an animal, can't use now, use next יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, right, or use next פסח. Pesach. You sanctified money
for פסח, Pesach, don't use it this פסח, Pesach, use it next
פסח. Pesach. So you've got a year that you can't use it
but you will use it at the end of a year. Is
that type of a thing a concern that we are afraid that
in the interim you might misuse? And that's the issue of תקלה
takala that we're saying in this case of money for the קרבן
פסח, korban Pesach, we see clearly it's a concern of not how
old the animal is, but are we afraid you'll misuse it? So
again at the extremes: out of your mind, out to pasture, never
going to be brought as a קרבן, korban, no problem. In the
other case, it's money sanctified nowadays, objects sanctified nowadays, there's nothing to
do with them, there's no בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Clearly that does
represent a very serious problem. How about something that's sanctified that you
will use, but you'll use not now, a year from now? And
that's the debate of is there a concern of תקלה Takalah or
not? And that has to do with the answer or the partial
answer to Rabbi Yehuda of even if you can't use the ox
and the goat, why not just use it next יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur? Okay, now we turn finally back to the משנה Mishna and
back to the actual עבודה Avoda on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So
we had remembered, done with the כהן Kohein doing all of the
blood of the ox and the goat on the inside on the
קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. First he did the incense, then he did
all of the blood in the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, then on
the פרוכת, Parochet, then on the מזבח, Mizbeiach, then he spilled the
blood on the base. Then it says he came to the goat.
So we had taken a step back to talk about again the
two goats and the drawing of the lots and all of those
issues. And now we once again and what happens if one of
the goats die? It's a whole thing about pairing it and doing
the lottery again and the whole thing. But now finally we are
done with the blood, done with the קטורת Ketores and we're finally
up to the goat, the שעיר המשתלח Sa'ir Hamishtaleiach that gets sent
away. So let's take a look. בא לו אצל שעיר המשתלח. Ba
lo eitzel sa'ir hamishtaleiach. He comes to the goat that is going
to be sent away. וסומך שתי ידיו עליו. Vesomeich shtei yadav alav.
He puts his two hands on it, ומתודה umitvadeh and he says
the וידוי, Viduy, the confession. וכך היה אומר Vekach haya omeir
and here's what he would say: אנא השם, Anna Hashem, oh God
please, please God, חטאו עוו פשעו chatu avu pash'u have sinned, have
transgressed, have rebelled לפניך עמך בית ישראל. lifanecha amcha beis Yisrael. There's
always the question about the order. You might remember that in the
past the משנה Mishna had a different order, the גמרא Gemara changed
the order. If the original גרסא girsa of this משנה Mishna probably
was also a different order, you look at the side you'll see
it references you to the printed משנה Mishna or the way it
appears in the משניות Mishnayot where the order is actually different. Okay,
so that's the whole lesson about which of what types of sins
these refer to. Unintentional, intentional, rebellious sins and which order they're mentioned
in. So you might remember that was a discussion before. לפניך עמך
בית ישראל, Lifanecha amcha beis Yisrael, your people Israel have sinned before
you. אנא השם, Anna Hashem, please God, כפר נא, kaper na, please
atone לחטאים ולעוונות ולפשעים, lachatayim vela'avonos velifsha'im,
the sins, the iniquities, and the rebellious sins שחטאו ושעוו ושפשעו לפניך
עמך בית ישראל shechatu veshavu shepash'u lifanecha amcha beis Yisrael that have
sinned before you, your people Israel ככתוב בתורת משה עבדך לאמור kakasuv
betoras Moshe avdecha leimore as it is written in the Torah of
Moshe your servant saying כי ביום הזה יכפר עליכם לטהר אתכם מכל
חטאתיכם לפני השם מכל חטאתיכם לטהר אתכם מכל חטאתיכם לפני השם תטהרו.
ki bayom hazeh yechaper aleichem letaher eschem mikol chatoseichem lifnei Hashem mikol
chatoseichem letaher eschem mikol chatoseichem lifnei Hashem titharu.
On this day it'll be atoned to you to purify you from
all of your sins before God you will be purified. והכהנים והעם
העומדים בעזרה Vehakohanim veha'am ha'omdim ba'azarah כשהיו שומעים שם המפורש שהוא יוצא
מפי כהן גדול, keshehayu shom'im shem hameforash shehu yotzei mipi kohein gadol,
then the כהנים Kohanim and the people that were standing in the
Temple courtyard when they heard the God's explicit name emerging from the
mouth of the כהן גדול, Kohein Gadol, היו כורעים ומשתחווים ונופלים על
פניהם hayu kor'im umishtachavim venoflim al pneihem
they would bow down and prostrate themselves and fall on their faces
ואומרים ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד ve'omrim baruch shem kevod malchuso
le'olam va'ed and say blessed is God's holy name forever and ever.
Notice, as opposed to our מחזור, machzor, it doesn't say ואף הוא
היה מתכוון לגמור את השם כנגד העם ואומר להם תטהרו, ve'af hu
haya miskavein ligmor es hashem keneged am ve'omeir lahem titharu, right? It's
very dramatic in our מחזור machzor because, you know, לפני השם lifnei
Hashem then we have this whole like climax, everybody bows down and
then after you talk about this whole moment of bowing down, he
finishes the פסוק passuk and says תטהרו, titharu, you'll be pure, right?
Very powerful like climax to that declaring that they will be pure.
You know, this doesn't have that. I mean, if they're bowing down
at God's name, then you do have then the sequence is right.
They bow down and then after as or after they're bowing down,
he says תטהרו, titharu, but you don't have it with that sort
of dramatic description in this משנה Mishna the same way you do
as we have it in our מחזור, machzor, in our liturgy. Okay,
ועוד, ve'od, okay, so that's he said the וידוי Viduy and we
had the same description of the וידוי Viduy when he did it
twice on his ox. But remember, he did not do a וידוי
Viduy on the goat of the people that the blood was done
on the inside. The וידוי Viduy that he does for the people
on their goat is only on this second goat that gets sent
away. מסרו למי שהיו מוליכו, Masru lemi shehayu molicho, he handed over
the goat to the person that would carry it, that would like
run with it to outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
over the cliff. הכל כשרים להוליכו, Hakol kesherim leholicho, anybody could do
this job of taking it to the cliff
אלא שעשו הכהנים
גדולים,
ella she'asu hakohanim gedolim, so Rashi doesn't have the גרסא girsa גדולים,
gedolim, many people don't have the גרסא girsa גדולים. gedolim. The כהנים
Kohanim made a practice, טבע, teva, made like an established practice שלא
היו מניחים את ישראל להוליכו. shelo hayu manichim es Yisrael leholicho. They
did not want to give this privilege to a ישראל. Yisrael. So
even though in theory it could have been done by anyone, you
know, the כהנים Kohanim were the ones that made the rule, it
was the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so they said we're not letting
ישראלים Yisraelim do it, we're only doing it
כהנים. Kohanim. אמר רבי יוסי מעשה והוליכו ארסלא מצפורין מצפורין Amar Rabbi
Yose ma'aseh veholicho Arselah mitziporin mitziporin
and if you look at the side some even say from Tzippori.
Anyway, there was a story that this person Arselah once did it,
וישראל היה veYisrael haya and he was a Jew, he was
a
ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, so they gave it to the person who would
by practice by generally be a כהן. Kohen. הכבש עשו לו מפני
הבבליים Hakevesh asu lo mipnei haBavliyim and they would make a ramp
to carry it out on because of the Babylonians. What's the Babylonians?
שהיו מתלשין בשערו, Shehayu metalshin bisaro, they would pull on his hair.
Whose hair? Presumably the hair of the guy running with it. Could
be the hair of the goat, but anyway they pull on his
hair ואומרים לו veomrim lo and say to him טול וצא טול
וצא. Tol vatzei, tol vatzei. Take it and get out, take it
and get out. I don't know how pulling his hair is going
to help him get out quicker, it's going to hold him back,
but anyway they were anyway they'd give him a, right, get rid
of our sins. So they'd give him a hard time, so they
wanted to give him a safe sort of exit so they made
like a protected ramp that he could run off on that nobody
would have access to so the people wouldn't be sort of yelling
at him and you know and attacking him. Who are they? I
don't know.
I don't know who they are obviously.
I don't know who they are. Anyway, the other possibility of the
other use of a ramp, I should say, is you know the
Temple Mount,
right there's like valleys right by it. So you know, you have
the Temple Mount here like הר Har Mount Olives is like here,
right? And there's the whole isn't this נחלא, Nachla, this is נחל
קדרון,
Nachal Kidron, right, in the valley here. So again if the ramp
was this way, right it lets you get over that whole valley
and get to, I guess I think they used a ramp like
that for the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah to go over. So to
get to because they did the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah on הר
הזיתים. Har HaZeitim. So anyway, so couldn't it could be that it's
not just a protective, it's also to give him a quicker access,
you know, out.
Yes, I'm thinking it's to get around to get around the steps
that you have to get go up to get to the עזרה.
Azarah.
Well, the same basic point. Right, you're at this elevation and a
ramp will help you get like over to the next mountain without
having to go down the whole way. All right, so now let's
take a look. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. ואילו
בני אהרן קדושיך לא קאמר. Ve'ilu bnei Aharon kedoshecha lo ka'amar. So
now becomes this whole interesting question we raised before. Which what thing
is atoning for whom for what? So here when he does the
goat that is being sent off, he only mentions בני ישראל, Bnei
Yisrael, he doesn't mention the כהנים. Kohanim. So מאן תנא? man tanna?
Who is this tanna? So אמר רבי ירמיה. Amar Rebbe Yirmiyah. Said
רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmiyah דלא כרבי יהודה. delo keRebbe Yehuda. It's not
like רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda דאי רבי יהודה הא אמר. dei Rebbe
Yehuda ha amar. Because רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said יש להם כפרה
בשעיר המשתלח yesh lahem kapara besair hamishtaleach that even the כהנים Kohanim
are atoned for with the שעיר המשתלח. sa'ir hamishtale'ach. It's not just
for ישראל. Yisrael.
And here you don't mention the כהנים, Kohanim, so it sounds like
it's just for ישראל. Yisrael. So אביי אמר Abaye amar אפילו תימא
רבי יהודה. afilu teima Rebbe Yehuda. Even if it's רבי יהודה. Rebbe
Yehuda. אטו כהנים לאו בכלל עמך ישראל נינהו? atu Kohanim lav bichlal
amcha Yisrael ninhu? Even though he didn't single them out, maybe דוקא
davka the reason not to single them out is because this represents
the totality of the people. That for issues of טומאת מקדש tumas
mikdash maybe they have different, you know, identities and different categories, but
for the rest of the sins, the whole point is to emphasize
that they're all one people, so you don't want to single them
out separately. Okay, so that's, so it's not clear whether they were
or not included. You cannot prove anything from their lack of being
identified. If anything, you could argue that that's to exactly to indicate
they're all in the same boat. So to remind you by the
way about what the different things did,
right? So the, so you have
right,
so you have the פר בפנים, par bifnim, right? And you have
the שעיר בפנים. sair bifnim. So what do those do? So, so
because they're בפנים, bifnim, right? Remember we had to, you know, the
Torah says וכיפר מקדש הקודש. vechiper mikdash hakodesh. It's all that atoning.
We've discussed many times that what it really you know, and what
in the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, it's this metaphysical cleansing
that national level of creating this ability for God to dwell within
the people. But from חז"ל's Chazal's perspective, it translates much more personally
for personal sin to atone for the sin that people had done,
not for the, you know, טומאה tumah and removing the טומאה tumah
but for a cleanse the sin. And for this specific sin, it's
this whole big ritual is to focus on one type of a
sin that was done, which is the sin of entering the מקדש
Mikdash when you are טמא. tamei. So these things do or these
are for טומאת מקדש tumas Mikdash but not again not cleansing the
מקדש Mikdash but the sin of טומאת מקדש tumas Mikdash according to
חז"ל. Chazal. And this is for the כהן Kohen כהנים Kohanim and
this is for ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, that's agreed upon. So and then
you have the שעיר המשתלח. Sa'ir HaMishtale'ach. So the easiest thing to
say about the שעיר המשתלח Sa'ir HaMishtale'ach is it's about the other
six hundred and twelve, right, all other sins. Okay, and it's for
everyone, כהנים, Kohanim, you know, it's for ישראל Yisrael plus כהנים. Kohanim.
ישראל Yisrael which includes כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, that's the easy idea. This
is, this is טומאת מקדש tumas Mikdash whether the sin of טומאת
מקדש tumas Mikdash or the metaphysical reality of טומאת מקדש tumas Mikdash
and this is for everybody else and for everybody's sins. Okay, that's
a nice way of thinking about it. But to remind you, the
alternative is to say no, because this gets a וידוי viduy plus
the דם, dam, the, you know, plus the ritual דם. dam. This
only has the דם, dam, and this has a וידוי viduy and
no דם. dam. Right? So So you have a lack of parallel
here, this gets a וידוי viduy and this doesn't. So that leaves
another opinion to say that even the כהנים's Kohanim's כפרה kappara for
the other 612 is different. And this וידוי viduy is the 612
all the other sins, right, the other sins for the כהנים. Kohanim.
And that this וידוי viduy is for the he calls it the
612 the other sins for ישראל. Yisrael. So according to that idea
you actually have that all of the כהנים's Kohanim's sins have, you
know, have a different כפרה. kappara. It's all about the blood on
the inside and this whole ritual is just for ישראל, Yisrael, which
I find, you know, more disturbing because it singles out the כהנים,
Kohanim, you know, even in their non-מקדש Mikdash capacity to have a
special atonement for their other sins and that this whole dramatic thing
is just for ישראל. Yisrael. So the כהנים Kohanim are always treated
like in this different way. The power of this is that what
this speaks towards is that the וידוי viduy by itself, right, not
the bringing of the blood, just the וידוי viduy achieves atonement. And
as we pointed out when we learned that last time, you know,
that's a major transition away from the מקדש Mikdash ritual. It's not
about the blood. What gets the whole כפרה kappara for all of
the other sins of the כהנים Kohanim is the וידוי, viduy, right,
and the complete moving away from the focus on the הקרבה hakrava
and how much is achieved just by the וידוי. viduy. And you'll
remember when we discussed the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtale'ach as well, we
discussed yesterday, it could drop dead once you've done the וידוי. viduy.
Now according to one of the opinions even without the וידוי, viduy,
just doing the גורל, goral, but that actually after the וידוי viduy
it could even drop dead and you're done. So again part of
what we're seeing here is the difference between כהנים Kohanim and the
people and how much the כהנים Kohanim have a separate כפרה kappara
from the people even in other sins, which probably
to me feels like a disturbing concept what exactly that signifies. It's
one thing to say in their מקדש Mikdash role, what does that
signify in terms of every other aspect? But the other interesting thing
we're seeing is the move towards the focus on the וידוי, viduy,
which really also sort of is that whole move shifting us towards
a post-type of a מקדש Mikdash reality. Okay, that's that approach. But
the simpler approach which he's talking about now is not the focus
on the וידוי, viduy, not too much distinguishing the כהנים, Kohanim, that
this is about טומאת מקדש tumat Mikdash and that's where they're different.
This is about all the other sins, that's all of כל ישראל
Klal Yisrael together. Yes.
You're saying that according to that second approach which you just surveyed?
Yes. If the וידוי viduy was the 612 for the כהנים Kohanim
then when is the and not for טומאת מקדש? tumat Mikdash?
No. What? What'd you say? What'd you say?
If you're saying that according to that second approach, yes, that the
דם dam
was for טומאת מקדש, tumat Mikdash, the וידוי viduy was for 612.
Yes, 613. Yeah yeah, but the וידוי viduy is right.
And then the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtale'ach was the וידוי viduy for
כל ישראל Klal Yisrael for all 612.
Yeah, because the דם dam there is still for... Okay. All right.
Okay, so מסרו למי שעתיד להוליכו, masru lemi she'atid leholicho, handed it
to the one that was going to carry it. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, our Rabbis taught: איש, ish, so it says ושלחו ביד איש
עתי, veshilacho beyad ish iti, he should send it away in the
hands of a ready person. איש ish להכשיר את הזר, lehachshir et
hazar, even a non-כהן, Kohen, any man.
עתי, iti, ready, I don't know, designated or prepared, כמו שהיה מזומן,
kemo she-haya mezuman, that he should be you know prepared. עתי, iti,
ואפילו בשבת. va'afilu be'Shabbat. Now עת et means time, so it's sort
of like the word you know במועדו, bemo'ado, so it means that
it could override other concerns. It could even be done on שבת.
Shabbat. We'll see why we need to say that.
עתי, iti, בעתו ואפילו בטומאה, be'ito va'afilu betum'ah, like the word במועדו
אפילו בשבת במועדו אפילו בטומאה. bemo'ado afilu be'Shabbat bemo'ado afilu betum'ah. So
here too it has to be done in its time even on
שבת Shabbat even בטומאה. betum'ah. Now we're going to analyze. איש להכשיר
את הזר פשיטא, ish lehachshir et hazar peshita, obviously a non-כהן Kohen
can do it, it's not an עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. דמהו דתימא, de-mahu detema, I might have thought כפרה כתיב
ביה, kappara ketiv beih, it says כפרה, kappara, it says right that
this thing is to achieve כפרה, kappara, קמשמע לן, ka mashma lan,
so therefore maybe it's like an עבודה. avodah. קמשמע לן. Ka mashma
lan. And you know it's similar to the whole issue about like
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah outside of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
right? What do you do about things that are somewhat קרבן korban
related but they're not in the מקדש? Mikdash? So this, at least
the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, you know it might be called a
חטאת chatat and whatever, but the blood is sprinkled towards the מקדש,
Mikdash, towards השם, Hashem, and that's you know one thing. This is
going לעזאזל. l'Azazel. This the whole point is it's not going להשם,
la-Hashem, it's going away from the מקדש, Mikdash, it's going לעזאזל. l'Azazel.
So that you don't need a כהן. Kohen. But again the possibility
that maybe you would, I want to remind you, the גמרא Gemara
also discussed the idea it has to be eight days old, it
can't have a מום. mum. So how much that while the תורה
Torah is clearly sort of saying one goes להשם la-Hashem and the
other goes לעזאזל, l'Azazel,
so you might want דווקא davka make it not so much like
not like a קרבן, korban, right? The גמרא Gemara is still pointing
out that there are some criteria that are similar, right, the eight
days, no מומים. mumim. So here it says maybe you would have
even needed a כהן, Kohen, but that it says not. Okay, so
עתו ואפילו בשבת *Iti ve'afillu beShabbos*, in its time even on שבת
*Shabbos*. למאי הלכתא *Lemai hilchesa*? Why do you have to tell me
even on שבת *Shabbos*? I mean if you could do it on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, you could do it on שבת *Shabbos*. And
anyway what's the violation of שבת *Shabbos* might you have? תחומים *Techumin*?
So אמר רב ששת *Amar Rav Sheshes*, תחומים דרבנן *techumin derabbanan*. It
says רב ששת *Rav Sheshes*, לומר שאם היה חולה מרכיבו על כתיפו
*lomar she'im hayah choleh markivo al kesifo*, to tell you that if
the animal was sick you could carry it on your shoulders. You
could be, you could be, you could be, you know, you could
do carrying on שבת *Shabbos* in order to get it to go
off the cliff. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, why
does, why is that, why do you need a פסוק *pasuk* to
tell me that? כמאן *Keman*? This is going דלא כרבי נתן *delo
keRabbi Natan*. דכי רבי rebbi. נתן *Dechi Rabbi Natan*, האמר *ha'amar* רבי
נתן *Rabbi Natan*, חי נושא את עצמו *chai nosei es atzmo*, that
if you carry a living person or a living animal on שבת
*Shabbos*, you don't violate שבת *Shabbos*. דרבנן *Drabbanan* it's a problem, but
biblically you don't violate שבת *Shabbos* because we say a living being
carries itself. Okay, partly supports its own weight. So therefore
no, so therefore this animal partly supports its own weight, so therefore
you shouldn't violate, so there should be no חידוש *chiddush* that you
could do it on שבת *Shabbos*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אפילו
תימא רבי נתן *afillu teima Rabbi Natan*, even רבי נתן *Rabbi Natan*
would agree that there is a violation of שבת *Shabbos* here. Why?
חולה שאני *Choleh shani*. If it's sick, it's different. If it's sick
then it is more like not carrying dead weight, not carrying its
own weight, and therefore it is an issue, which raises interesting questions,
you know, about carrying an infant and at what age is an,
do we say that it's not enough that something is alive, it
has to be more, you know, mobile or able to hold its
own weight in order to not be this biblical problem and only
get you down to a rabbinic problem. So that's an interesting question
in שבת *Shabbos*, but we see that it's not true that every
live thing is considered to be נושא את עצמו *nosei es atzmo*.
If it is sick, we don't say that. So there is a
שבת *Shabbos* violation. One second. So the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* still question is
going to be that's all very nice that there's a, that there
could be a שבת *Shabbos* violation and the פסוק *pasuk* has to
allow it, but what makes שבת *Shabbos* different than יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*? You know, you would have allowed it on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* has the same restrictions. Why do you
need a special פסוק *pasuk* for שבת *Shabbos*? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, אמר
רפרם *Amar Rafram*, זאת אומרת *zos omeres*, the fact that you needed
a פסוק *pasuk* for שבת *Shabbos* tells you, עירוב והוצאה לשבת *eiruv
vehotza'ah leShabbos*, that there is a idea of עירוב *eiruv*. Now that's
rabbinic. The real point about this is the second word, הוצאה *hotza'ah*.
There is a biblical restriction, מלאכה *melachah* of carrying on שבת *Shabbos*,
and therefore the rabbis needed to institute עירוב *eiruv* because you're dealing
in a realm where there's restrictions of carrying. And here's the real
חידוש *chiddush*: ואין עירוב והוצאה ליום הכיפורים *ve'ein eiruv vehotza'ah leYom Hakippurim*.
On יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, there's no prohibition, at least biblically, of
carrying and therefore no need of rabbinic עירוב *eiruv*. It's like יום
טוב *Yom Tov*. There's no, there's no restriction of carrying. How do
you know that?
Because because if there were the rabbinic, if there were the biblical
restrictions of carrying on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, you then, whatever you,
you didn't need this חידוש *chiddush* for שבת *Shabbos*. You would need
the חידוש *chiddush* for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* to tell me you
could carry it if the animal is sick. The fact that you're
telling me you only need to tell it to me for שבת
*Shabbos* and not יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* means that on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* there's no problem of carrying. Now that is the גמרא
*Gemara* here makes that statement without challenging it, which is crazy. Since
when did we ever hear that you could carry on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*, that יום כיפור'ס *Yom Kippur's* only reason you can carry
on יום טוב *Yom Tov* is because it's part of this whole
thing about things that are related to food preparation, which you don't
have a license for on, on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So if
you take a look at תוספות *Tosafos*, אמר רפרם זאת אומרת *Amar
Rafram zos omeres*, תוספות *Tosafos* says, אמרינן בפרק אמרו לו *amrinan beperek
amru lo*, we say in the גמרא *Gemara* in כריתות *Kerisos* that
דרפרם בדותא היא *deRafram bedusa hi*. This statement of רפרם *Rafram* is
like basically is a joke, is foolishness, is like completely, you know,
not true. Why? דפרחה לה דלמא שאני שלוחו של שר דאשתרי ביום
הכיפורים בכך *Deparcha lah dilma shani shilucho shel sar de'ishtarei beYom Hakippurim
bekach*. The reason you don't need a פסוק *pasuk* to tell me
that if it was just יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* you could do
it is because on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* you're given license to
do whatever is needed to do for the עבודה *avodah*. The same
way you can שחט *shacht* the animals on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
for the עבודה *avodah*. So it's not true that, obviously you can't
carry on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* either, but it's not such a
חידוש *chiddush* to tell me you can violate יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
to do the עבודה *avodah*. Because you can violate because because the
whole point is that this is a עבודה *avodah* for יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*. The חידוש *chiddush* is that even if it's also שבת
*Shabbos*, although the restrictions are the same as יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*,
but because it's specifically שבת *Shabbos*, you might think you don't have
particular license to do a יום כיפור עבודה *Yom Kippur avodah* on
שבת *Shabbos* and it's telling me that you do. So the חידוש
*chiddush* is that you can do it even on שבת *Shabbos* slash
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* even if it requires carrying. And although רפרם
*Rafram* says from here we can infer since we need to mention
שבת *Shabbos* we can infer that there's no prohibition of carrying on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, please do not be misled that way. There
is a biblical prohibition of carrying on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. That
is not the point. We're just singling out שבת *Shabbos* to tell
me that שבת *Shabbos* even though, even though it's not, even though
it's a יום כיפור עבודה *Yom Kippur avodah* and the overriding of
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* is more obvious, it can even override שבת
*Shabbos* if you need to carry it. Yes.
תוספות *Tosafos* saying to read רפרם *Rafram* sarcastically?
No. בדותא *Bedusa* does not mean he was sarcastic. בדותא *Bedusa* means
that the later גמרא *Gemara* has completely rejected it. When you say
that's a joke, okay, it means like it's not even a position
worth thinking, worth considering. It's like, you know, that's what it means.
Not that he was being sarcastic. Right.
And
he was just saying it's a joke.
Right. Exactly, rejected. Exactly.
A שעיר *se'ir* that's a חולה *choleh* is still able to be
carried out to the עזאזל *Azazel*, but a שעיר *se'ir* that's a
חולה *choleh* is not going to be שחט *shechted* for the inside.
Right, although how sick is sick that it stops being legitimate for
a קרבן *korban* is a good point.
If it can't walk, right, that's probably a point.
Right, right, well, has to walk a good distance, but yes.
All right, you use עבודה *avodah* for עבודה
*avodah*.
Well, okay, that gets to an interesting question, like we mentioned before
about it having to be unblemished. Is there an idea of being
ideal if you're sending it לעזאזל *la'Azazel*, right? Normal things we say
about certain ideas about how fit the animal has to be is
because you're bringing it to God, הקריבהו נא לפחתך *Hakrivehu na le'pachatecha*,
etc. So maybe that doesn't apply לעזאזל *la'Azazel*. That's a good question.
All right, let's keep on going.
Like חולה *choleh* is a מום *mum*, isn't it?
Like חולה *choleh* and זקן *zaken* and things like that? No, it's
not a מום *mum*. It's a different concern about whether it's appropriate,
which is the issue that Charlie just made, that it might not
be appropriate as a קרבן *korban*, but it's still acceptable לעזאזל *la'Azazel*.
But it's decided as a קרבן *korban* by the lottery.
Right, by the גורל *goral*.
But it's gotten sick after the lottery. Not every sick can be
brought as a קרבן *korban*. Not just running a little fever or
whatever. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Okay, איתיבי
אפילו בטומאה *eitivi afilu be'tumah*, it overrides טומאה *tumah* concerns. למאי הלכתא
*le'mai hilchata*, for what purpose are we saying it overrides טומאה *tumah*?
So what would be a case where there would be a טומאה
*tumah* concern? אמר רב ששת *amar Rav Sheshet*, לומר שנטמא משלחו *lomar
she'nitma meshallcho*. משלחו *meshallcho*, if the guy that you had designated to
carry it has become טמא *tamei*, נכנס טמא לעזרה ומשלחו *nichnas tamei
la'azarah u'meshallcho*, you can, he can enter טמא *tamei* into the עזרה
*azarah* and you can send it off. Just find someone else. You
don't have to get another guy. So here's a fascinating idea that
because it says עיתי *itti* like מזומן *mezuman*, the guy has to
be designated and ready, presumably once you appoint a guy, that can
override even if he's טמא *tamei*, even though you could get another
guy. Now, again, is it because of a concept like טומאה הותרה
בציבור *tumah hutra be'tzibbur*, we don't have to look for alternatives? Right,
remember there was that idea, how much you even have to care
about alternatives? Or maybe it's there's a special status of עיתי *itti*,
there's a special status of the guy that was originally designated and
he has more
status, and therefore we're going to go with him even if it
means having to have him come טמא *tamei* into the בית המקדש
*Beit HaMikdash*.
They don't want him to just
walk that few feet until we get... Well, that's also a question.
Why not have the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* walk to the edge
of the עזרה *azarah* and hand it to him? But it says
ושלחו *ve'shillcho*, you know, sounds like the way the תורה Torah *Torah*
describes it, that it's being done in the עזרה *azarah*.
And entirely by him. Yeah.
Right. שאלו את רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *sha'alu et Rabbi Eliezer*. Now
we're going to have some interesting stories. They asked רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, חולה מהו שירכיבנו על כתיפו *choleh mahu she'yarkivennu al
ketefo*, if the animal got sick, can he carry it on his
shoulders, the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*? אמר להם *amar lahem*, he said
to them, יכול להרכיב אני ואתם *yachol le'harkiv ani ve'atem*, you know,
the animal can carry me and you. Okay. Whoa, what answer was
that? So basically what we're going to see is, you might remember
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* very much believed that, you know,
that תורה Torah שבעל פה *Torah She'be'al Peh* was just מסורה *masorah*,
just handing over what you learned from your רבי *rebbe*. And he
never wanted to say anything he didn't hear from his רבי *rebbe*.
So since, even though he knew the הלכה *halacha* here, this is
the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it, I'll tell you what the
מהרש"א *Maharsha* says in a minute, even though he knew the הלכה
*halacha*, he didn't want to tell them because he didn't hear it
from his רבי *rebbe*, so he gave them some silly answer. Yeah,
what do you mean if it got sick? You don't think it's
a good healthy animal? It can carry the two of us.
Oh, he doesn't mean the person?
No, no, that we'll get to. חולה משלחו מהו *choleh meshallcho mahu*,
let's say the שליח *shaliach* got sick, what's the story? מהו שישלחנו
ביד אחר *mahu she'yishlachenu be'yad acher*, can you have another person carry
it? אמר להם *amar lahem*, he said to them, יהא בשלום אני
ואתם *yehei be'shalom ani ve'atem*, you know, you and I should be
in peace, it should all be good. What? Anyway, דחפו ולא מת
מהו שירד אחריו וימיתנו *dachfo ve'lo met mahu she'yered achrav viyemitennu*, let's
say he pushed it off the cliff and it didn't die, can
he go after it and kill it? אמר להם *amar lahem*, he
said to them, כן יאבדו כל אויביך ה' *ken yovedu kol oyvecha
Hashem*, this is how all your enemies should die, God, by being
pushed off the cliff. All of these non-responses.
And וחכמים אומרים *ve'Chachamim omrim*, and
the חכמים *Chachamim* say, חולה *choleh*, if the animal got sick, מרכיבו
על כתיפו *markivo al ketefo*, carry it on your shoulder, like we
said. חולה משלחו *choleh meshallcho*, if the guy that you sent it
off got sick, so you were planning to send it with, got
sick, ישלחנו ביד אחר *yeshlachenu be'yad acher*, have somebody else do it.
דחפו ולא מת *dachfo ve'lo met*, if you pushed it off and
it didn't die, ירד אחריו וימיתנו *yered achrav viyemitennu*, then you follow
go after it and you kill it yourself. Now, fine, that's so
the very bizarre responses. And right, yet רש"י Rashi *Rashi* just says
they really didn't mean anything, it was just a way of avoiding
answering the question. The מהרש"א *Maharsha* has an interesting read. Wait a
minute, what'd you say? Why record it? Yeah, why record it? Good
question. Just to show how far he would go not to give
a straight answer. But the מהרש"א *Maharsha* gives an interesting way of
explaining that he actually is giving an answer, and his answer actually
is different than that of the חכמים *Chachamim*. Okay. So remember there
was a question before if it got sick, maybe that's a שבת
*Shabbat* violation because maybe it's dead weight. So his first answer... Answer
was יכול *Yachol*, what was his first answer when he said יכול
הוא להרכיב אני ואתם *Yachol hu l'harkiv ani va'atem*, which means like
if it's healthy and it can carry us, then we can carry
it, but if it's sick and it can't carry us, then it's
dead weight and then you're not allowed to carry it because it
would be a violation that he actually is arguing on the previous
position. Okay, and how about the issue about חלה משלחו מהו שישלחנו
*Chala mishlocho mahu she-yishlachenu*? So he actually, the מהרש"א *Maharsha* has it
slightly different, suggests a slight change in the גרסא *girsa*. He says
not היי בשלום אני ואתה *Hei b'shalom ani v'ata*, but he changes
the מ *mem* to a ח *ches*. היי בשילוח אני ואתה *Hei
b'shiloach ani v'ata*. Why would you have to use the sick guy
to send it off? Just, you know, you or I could go
and take care of it, someone else could go ahead and take
care of it. Okay, and then the last one, what happens if
it didn't die? He says כן יאבדו כל אויביך השם *Ken yovdu
kol oyvecha Hashem*, as as if to say it's not going to
happen, it'll definitely die. Okay, and the rabbis say, no, you can
carry it, if he gets sick, he can appoint another person. The
מהרש"א *Maharsha* says the question of getting sick is, if he gets
sick, who has to appoint the other person? Does the כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol* have to appoint the other person, or can the שליח
*shaliach* who was the guy who was given the job, can he
create a substitute? So he wants to say that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* says, you or I could do it, meaning he can't make
us a substitute. Let the כהנים *Kohanim* pick somebody else to do
it. Let the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* pick somebody else to do
it. And the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* response is, no, the guy who was
given the job, he can appoint a substitute. That raises I think
an interesting conceptual question, right? Once you appointed this guy as the
job, is it now his job? And if he can't do it,
he can pass it over to someone else? Or no, if he
can't do it, ultimately it's the כהן'ס *Kohen's* concern, כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol*, the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, and they create the substitute. That's
how the מהרש"א *Maharsha* wanted to read it, and wanted to read
that his response 'you or I could do it' means he can't
appoint the
substitute, anyone else could do it, let the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*
figure out who's going to be the next person. Yeah.
It is two things. One is then the point is that he
sees לכתחילה *lechatchila* not בדיעבד *bedieved* because, you know, right, בדיעבד *bedieved*
he finished and nobody appointed a backup?
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
Because it's like a... And then, who appoints this guy to begin
with?
Yeah, that's not clear. Clearly somehow the connection... Exactly, well that's what
the מהרש"א *Maharsha* says, but this says, he is, ישלחנו ביד אחר
*Yishlachenu b'yad acher*, the way the מהרש"א *Maharsha* reads the debate is
that he gets to choose who the next guy is. Okay. Now
that we're having interesting answers of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* not giving
straight answers, we're going to have one other case. שאלו את רבי
אליעזר *Sha'alu es Rabbi Eliezer*, they asked רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, פלוני
מהו לעולם הבא *Ploni mahu l'Olam HaBa*? Is so-and-so going to get
עולם הבא *Olam HaBa*? אמר להם *Amar lahem*, לא שאלתוני אלא על
פלוני *Lo she'altuni ela al Ploni*. Why ask me about that guy,
ask me about the other guy. Now there's questions of גרסאות *girsaos*.
Other גרסאות *girsaos* says that they said back to him, okay, what
about the other guy? So he said, why ask me about the
other guy, ask me about the first guy. Which was just a
way of constantly avoiding the question. Now מהו להציל רועה כבשה מן
הארי *Mahu l'hatzil ro'eh kivsa min ha'ari*? Can the now our גרסא
*girsa* is, can the shepherd save a lamb from the lion? אמר
להם *Amar lahem*, לא שאלתוני אלא על הכבשה *Lo she'altuni ela al
hakivsa*. Why didn't you ask me about the lamb, how about asking
me about the shepherd? So they said, fine, מהו להציל הרועה מן
הארי *Mahu l'hatzil haro'eh min ha'ari*? Can you save the shepherd from
the lion? אמר להם *Amar lahem*, לא שאלתוני אלא על הרועה *Lo
she'altuni ela al haro'eh*. Why you only ask me about the shepherd,
ask me about the lamb. So now what is this about? So
תוספות *Tosafos* quotes רבנו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* with a brilliant explanation. He
says the first issue about whether they were asking about a guy
he wouldn't give a straight answer to, the person they were asking
was about אבשלום *Avshalom*. Okay, that we're talking about issues about דוד
המלך *Dovid HaMelech* and אבשלום *Avshalom* and so on. And that אבשלום
*Avshalom* slept with דוד'ס פילגש *Dovid's pilegesh*. So is that a real
case of adultery or not a case of adultery? He didn't want
to give them a straight answer whether אבשלום *Avshalom* was going to
get עולם הבא *Olam HaBa*, so maybe they switched the conversation and
asked him about, okay, let's not talk about אבשלום *Avshalom*, let's talk
about שלמה המלך *Shlomo HaMelech*, like, you know, because of all the
wives he had, whatever, the 400 wives. Oh, why ask me about
שלמה *Shlomo*, let's talk about אבשלום *Avshalom*. And then the question about
הכבשה *hakivsa*, הרועה *haro'eh* and הארי *ha'ari* is great. He says you
know what that's talking about? Talking about בת שבע *Bas Sheva*, אוריה
*Uriah* and דוד *Dovid*. דוד *Dovid* is הארי *ha'ari*, the lion, who
is coming to attack both the lamb, בת שבע *Bas Sheva*, and
הרועה *haro'eh*, the shepherd, right, which is אוריה *Uriah*. So he says,
can you save the lamb from the lion? Like was דוד *Dovid*
committing adultery? Was this an act of like the lion attacking the
lamb? You know, obviously it sounds like it's adultery, but חז"ל Chazal
*Chazal* want to read it as though אוריה *Uriah* had given a
גט *get* or whatever. He says, oh, why ask me about the
lamb? Ask me about what דוד *Dovid* did to אוריה *Uriah*, the
shepherd. Okay, was that murder, what he did, you know, he had
אוריה *Uriah* killed. But again חז"ל *Chazal* want to read it like
it was because אוריה *Uriah* was a מורד במלכות *mored b'malchus*, you
know, and אוריה *Uriah* was, you know, rejecting דוד'ס *Dovid's* authority, they
tried to justify what דוד *Dovid* did. Okay, so how about what
the lion attacked the shepherd? Why ask me about the shepherd? Ask
me about the lamb. So he was constantly avoiding answering those hard
questions. Okay. ממזר mamzer. מהו לירש *Mamzer mahu l'yarash*? Can a ממזר
mamzer *mamzer* get ירושה yerusha. *yerusha*, inherit his father? Because as opposed
to, you know, the common conception of bastard, and a bastard isn't
a legitimate child and doesn't get inheritance, according to חז"ל *Chazal*, a
ממזר mamzer? *mamzer* is considered the recognized child of the father. He
just can't marry, but he's a recognized child.
but the basic answer is, we do know that he can do
ייבום yibbum, again, he has to do חליצה chalitza because it's אסור
assur to marry, but he actually is in the category of כתינא
k'tzina a brother for purposes of ייבום, and similarly he's a brother
for purposes of ירושה. So that actually is an answer to that
question or a partial answer. מהו לסוד את ביתו? mahu lesode et
beto? Can a person plaster his house? Meaning is there a concern
of זכר לחורבן zecher l'churban that you're not allowed to plaster your
house? That's the way רש"י reads the question. So he said, מהו
לסוד את קברו? mahu lesode et kivro? Why ask me about plastering
the, what do you call it? About plastering the grave? Okay, which
is, which רש"י does say, doesn't really explain what the significance about
that is. The ב"ח Bach says that it's questions about that we're
still talking about the ממזר. Do you plaster his grave or do
you not, which was something they would do to honor the grave
or do you not, so people understand that he was a ממזר
and his kids were a ממזר? Anyway, לא מקני, lo mikneh, so
all of these things, לא מקני שפליגן בדברים, lo mikneh shep'ligan bidvarim,
not because he's trying to distract them with other words, which is
exactly what it sounds like, אלא מפני שלא אמר דבר שלא שמע
מרבו מעולם. ella mipnei shelo amar davar shelo shama merabbo meolam. He
didn't want to say something that he had never heard from his
רבי. So again, the funny thing is, okay, that might be why
he's distracting them with saying something else, but it's not like he's
not distracting them.
This is in סוכה. Sukkah.
Exactly. Okay, let's just read a little bit more, I know we're
over, but give me just two more minutes. שאלה אשה חכמה את
רבי אליעזר. shaala isha chachama et Rabbi Eliezer.
A wise woman asked רבי אליעזר, ואחר שחטאו העגל שוים, v'achar shechetau
ha'egel shavin, since everybody worshipped the עגל, egel, מפני מה אין מיתתן
שוה? mipnei ma ein mitatan shava? Why did they get different deaths?
On the one hand
it says that they went through and they killed people by the
sword, משה ולוי, Moshe v'Levi, and then it says that God smote
the people and there was some type of pestilence or דבר, dever,
and then it says that he made them drink the water that
he ground up the עגל egel and presumably that was like סוטה,
Sotah, where, you know, the תורה Torah doesn't describe this, but חז"ל
understand like, you know, like their stomachs explode. So why all these
different deaths? What merit is that? אמר לה, amar lah, he said
to her, ready רבקה? Rivka? אין חכמה לאשה אלא בפלך. ein chochma
l'isha ella b'palech.
There's no wisdom for a woman except in her פלך, palech, right,
the thing that you use for doing, not knitting, weaving. Okay, which
is why they call the girls' school in Israel פלך. Pelech. Yeah,
they do it as intentionally ironic. וכן הוא אומר, v'chen hu omer,
וכל אשה חכמת לב בידיה טוו. v'chol isha chachamat lev b'yadeha tavu.
All the wise women, they wove. So, you know, he says, what's
a woman doing asking תורה Torah questions? If you have any intelligence,
you should go do weaving. Not a very positive attitude towards women,
which also comes up in that whole famous משנה סוטה Mishnah Sotah
of כל המלמד את בתו תורה, kol hamelamed et bito Torah, and
so on, that רבי אליעזר takes a very negative attitude. I believe
it's רבי אליעזר who says, מוטב שישרפו דברי תורה ואל ימסרו
לנשים. muttav sheyisrafu divrei Torah v'al yimasru l'nashim. Better that words of
תורה should be burned rather than given over to women. So he
had an extremely negative attitude towards women, also interesting to see his
own relationship with his wife. Lots to be said about that. איתמר,
itmar, now that we mentioned this question about why they got different
punishments, we might as well answer it. Won't answer the woman, but
it's a question that needs
an answer. So רב ולוי, Rav v'Levi, חד אמר, chad amar, זבח
וקיטר בסייף. zivach v'kiter b'sayif. The one that actually slaughtered animals to
the עגל, egel, which is real עבודה זרה avoda zara and burnt
them up, they get killed בסייף, b'sayif, which is like the
real, you know, execution. גיפף ונישק, gibeph v'nishak, if he hugged and
kissed the עגל, egel, that's not, that's not an actual act of
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, so במיתה, b'mita, that's some divine death, you
know, it's they died, but not through like an execution. שמח בלבו,
simach b'libo, if you were rejoicing in your heart but didn't actually
act upon it, בהדרוקן, badrokan, that's when you would get this sickness
and your stomach would explode from the water. That was a more
private type of a way. וחד אמר, v'chad amar, the other said,
עדים והתראה בסייף. edim v'hatraah b'sayif. Witnesses and warning, that's again like
a court type of an execution, בסייף, b'sayif, you get the sword.
עדים בלא התראה במיתה, edim b'lo hatraah b'mita, witnesses without warning, במיתה,
b'mita, you get the heavenly death. לא עדים ולא התראה, lo edim
v'lo hatraah, no witnesses and no warning, but you still did the
worship, בהדרוקן, badrokan, you would explode. Now again, why witnesses make it
different since in the end there wasn't, you weren't warned and you
couldn't be executed by the court. It might be similar to the
whole idea of the drinking of the water is like the סוטה,
Sotah, because the סוטה Sotah does her sin without any witnesses. The
whole point of the סוטה Sotah is there is no witnesses. So
they want to ascribe that to the case of no witnesses. And
maybe somebody who does it in front of people and with witnesses
even without warning is a more serious thing. You're willing to do
it in public even though it's not yet fit for execution. Okay,
last line and we'll end with this. אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav
Yehuda, שבטו של לוי לא עבד עבודה כוכבים. shivto shel Levi lo
avad avoda kochavim. לוי Levi was never part of the עגל, egel,
שנאמר, shene'emar, ויעמוד משה בשער המחנה vayayamod Moshe b'shaar hamachaneh and he
said מי לה' אלי mi l'Hashem elai and all of לוי Levi
gathered to him. יתיב רבינא וקאמר להאי שמעתא. yasiv Ravina v'ka'amar lehai
shemaita. So רבינא Ravina was saying this over. איתיבו בני רב פפא
בר אבא לרבינא. itvu b'nei Rav Pappa bar Abba l'Ravina. So the
sons of רב פפא Rav Pappa asked him, האומר לאביו ולאמו לא
ראיתיו. ha'omer l'aviv u'le'imo lo reitihu. The תורה says that לוי, Levi,
right in האזינו, Ha'azinu, would ignore mother and father and children and
was willing to defend God's honor. Well, mother and father and children
are all from שבט לוי, Shevet Levi, so how could you say
none of לוי Levi sinned? So the גמרא says here is the
answer. אביו Aviv doesn't literally mean his father. It means אבי אמו
מישראל, avi imo mi'Yisrael, his grandfather through his mother, who was not
a לוי. Levi. אחיו, Echav, his brothers, doesn't mean his brothers on
his father's side. אחיו מאמו מישראל, achav m'imo mi'Yisrael, the half brother
on his mother's side who wasn't a לוי. Levi. בניו, Banav, his
children that it says he didn't recognize them and was willing to
stand up for God's honor, doesn't mean directly his sons, it means
בני בתו מישראל, b'nei bito mi'Yisrael, his grandson through his daughter who
was a ישראל Yisrael and not a לוי. Levi. And that's that
nobody from לוי Levi actually sinned. Okay, for tomorrow.